Guide to the Walter L. Pforzheimer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walter L. Pforzheimer papers
1548-2001
1940-1995
GEN MSS 817
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
133.09
(147 boxes) + 9 broadside, 2 cold storage, 9 art, 1 roll
The Walter L. Pforzheimer Papers contain personal correspondence, diaries, writings, notes, and family papers; correspondence, reports, and other documents relating to the United States Army during World War II, the Central Intelligence Agency, the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, and the United States Defense Intelligence College; historical manuscripts and related materials collected by Pforzheimer concerning the history of military intelligence, including autograph documents, signed, by European heads of state and American presidents, seventeenth-twentieth centuries; prints, posters, and newspapers, including rare seventeenth-twentieth century items relating to Molière and other subjects; framed oil paintings and prints; book collecting notes, lists, vendor receipts, and card catalogs; rare postage stamps, including propaganda and forgeries; photographs, glass and film negatives, glass stereographs, and photograph albums; video and audio recordings, including interviews with Pforzheimer and presentations by him; microfilms; computer disks; and objects collected by Pforzheimer, including Molière medals, military decorations, and memorabilia relating to his intelligence career.
Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift and bequest of Walter L. Pforzheimer (Yale 1935, 1938L), 2000-2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Restricted pending full processing. Access to specific items may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 56-59, 60 (Art), 141-143 (Art), 143a (Art), 141-144 (Art), 145-150, 151 (Art), 152, 153 (Art), 154-158, 159 (Art), and 161-162 (Cold storage): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult Access Services.
Boxes 160 and 165 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available. For further information consult Access Services.
Associated Materials
Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Historical Manuscripts (GEN MSS 838)
Walter L. Pforzheimer Collection of Frank Richard Stockton (YCAL MSS 560)
Books owned by Pforzhemer may be found in the online catalog by a keyword search on the phrase "From the library of Walter L. Pforzheimer".
Walter L. Pforzheimer (1914-2003)
Walter L. Pforzheimer, lawyer, intelligence officer, and book collector. Pforzheimer was born in Port Chester, New York, in 1914, and graduated from Yale College (1935) and Yale Law School (1938). Pforzheimer began his intelligence career in the United States Army, 1942-1945, in the Office of Strategic Services and as an Army Air Force intelligence officer. He was one of the founders of the Central Intelligence Agency in 1946, and as a CIA legislative counsel and liaison to Congress assisted in drafting the 1947 National Security Act. In 1956, he founded the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, which he curated until his retirement in 1974. In retirement, he continued to work for the CIA and taught at the Defense Intelligence College. Pforzheimer died in Washington, D.C., in 2003.
Pforzheimer came from a family of book collectors: his father, also named Walter Pforzheimer (1883-1955), collected French armorial bindings and assembled a virtually complete collection of Molière; his uncle Carl H. Pforzheimer (1879-1957) collected Percy Bysshe Shelley and his circle. Pforzheimer inherited and augmented his father's collections, and assembled his own collection of American novelist Frank Richard Stockton. In addition to curating the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, Pforzheimer built a personal collection of books and manuscripts documenting the history of military intelligence. Elected to the Yale Library Associates board of trustees in 1936, Pforzheimer was a life-long trustee and donor to the Yale Libraries. He donated his book and manuscript collections of Molière, French armorial bindings, Frank Richard Stockton, and military intelligence to the Beinecke Library in 2001.
Sources:
Peake, Hayden B. "Walter Pforzheimer -- Lawyer, Intelligence Officer, Bibliophile." In: In the Name of Intelligence: Essays in Honor of Walter Pforzheimer (Washington: NIBC Press, c1994).
"Walter L. Pforzheimer, CIA's First Curator, Dies at 88." Washington Post (2003 February 12).
Scope and Contents
The Walter L. Pforzheimer Papers contain personal correspondence, diaries, writings, notes, and family papers; correspondence, reports, and other documents relating to the United States Army during World War II, the Central Intelligence Agency, the CIA's Historical Intelligence Collection, and the United States Defense Intelligence College; historical manuscripts and related materials collected by Pforzheimer concerning the history of military intelligence, including autograph documents, signed, by European heads of state and American presidents, seventeenth-twentieth centuries; prints, posters, and newspapers, including rare seventeenth-twentieth century items relating to Molière and other subjects; framed oil paintings and prints; book collecting notes, lists, vendor receipts, and card catalogs; rare postage stamps, including propaganda and forgeries; photographs, glass and film negatives, glass stereographs, and photograph albums; video and audio recordings, including interviews with Pforzheimer and presentations by him; microfilms; computer disks; and objects collected by Pforzheimer, including Molière medals, military decorations, and memorabilia relating to his intelligence career.
Research strengths include the history of military intelligence; World War II intelligence and propaganda; Pforzheimer's intelligence career, the formation and early history of the Central Intelligence Agency, and development of the Central Intelligence Agency's Historical Intelligence Collection; book and manuscript collecting, and the development of Pforzheimer's collections of military intelligence, Molière, French armorial bindings, and Frank Richard Stockton; postal history and stamp collecting; American twentieth century politics and government; and the Pforzheimer family.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: November 2000 Acquisition, April 2003 Acquisition, January 2005 Acquisition, and Unidentified Acquisitions.
Armorial bindings -- France; Book collecting -- United States; Book collectors -- United States; Intelligence officers -- United States; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Military intelligence; Military intelligence -- United States; Stamp collecting -- United States; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Autochromes (photographs) -- United States -- 20th Century; Born digital; Electronic documents -- United States -- 20th Century; Medals -- France -- 17th century; Negatives (photographic) -- United States -- 20th Century; Oil paintings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Postage stamps -- 20th Century; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Stereographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Video recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Videocassettes; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th Century; Intelligence officers -- United States -- 20th Century; Molière, 1622-1673; Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003; Pforzheimer, Walter L. (Walter Lionel), 1914-2003; Pforzheimer family; Stockton, Frank R., 1834-1902; Defense Intelligence College (U.S.); United States. Army Air Forces; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; United States. Central Intelligence Agency. Historical Intelligence Collection; United States. Office of Strategic Services
- November 2000 Acquisition, 46.46; (53 boxes) + 5 broadside folders, 1 object storage item, 1 roll
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Military Intelligence; Historical Manuscripts; and Military Intelligence and Personal Papers. Folders within subseries are unarranged. Folder contents have not been verified.
  Scope and Contents
  Subseries reflect a partial sort conducted during preliminary processing; actual contents overlap between subseries. The Military Intelligence subseries contains materials relating to Pforzheimer's military service and CIA career. The Historical Manuscripts subseries contains manuscripts and related materials collected by Pforzheimer concerning the history of military intelligence, roughly subdivided by country or time period. The Military Intelligence and Personal Papers subseries contains materials similar to the first two subseries, as well as documentation of Pforzheimer's book and manuscript collecting; postage stamps collected by him; family papers; photographic materials, prints, and visual art; audio and video recordings; and objects.
  - Military Intelligence
    - United States Army
      - Stamps, 1944-1997, undated; 9 (Box 1)
      - Stamps, 1944-1997, undated; 9 (Box 1)
      - Stamps, 1944-1997, undated; 9 (Box 1)
      - Stamps, 1944-1997, undated; 9 (Box 1)
      - Stamps, 1944-1997, undated; 8 (Box 1)
      - Stamp articles, 1963-1987, undated; 4 (Box 1)
      - Stamps-Hitler, 1968 (Box 1)
      - Stamp hinges, undated; 3 (Box 1)
      - Stamp albums, undated; 3 (Box 2)
      - Stamp album, undated (Box 3)
      - Information compiled by Louis Budenz, managing editor of the Daily Worker, for the House Committee on Un-American Activities, undated; 9 (Box 4)
      - Information compiled by Louis Budenz, managing editor of the Daily Worker, for the House Committee on Un-American Activities, undated; 9 (Box 4)
      - Information compiled by Louis Budenz, managing editor of the Daily Worker, for the House Committee on Un-American Activities, undated; 3 (Box 4)
      - Berlin [Prussian Finance Minister], Jul 1939
      - Golden Buch der Flieger, undated
      - Field army notebook, undated (Box 4)
      - Security circulars, 1943 (Box 4)
      - Army Air Forces Intelligence School: manuals, 1942; 3 (Box 4)
      - Amusategui, Lorenza Vazquez de: Personal narrative in re "The Miss U" undercover group, undated (Box 4)
      - Photograph, undated (Box 4)
      - Active duty, HQ Strikecom, MacDill AFB, 1963 (Box 4)
      - AAF OCS Miami Beach class notes of Lt. Walter L. Pforzheimer, Harrisburg map overlays., 1942 (Box 4)
        Also notes from (May/43) AAFSAT, Orlando
      - Cloth maps, undated; 3 (Box 4)
      - Security documents and notes, 1944-1952 (Box 4)
      - German cross, 1941 (Box 4)
      - Data on Amphibious Command, 1943 (Box 4)
      - Amphibious Command, 1943 (Box 5)
      - MacDill Air Force Base: miscellaneous papers, 1943; 2 (Box 5)
      - Intelligence school: notes and class room handouts, circa 1943; 4 (Box 5)
      - German and French printed ephemera, 1917, undated (Box 5)
      - Martin, Ray: "Stalag Luft," typescript, mimeograph, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
      - "Operation Siren:" typescript, 1945 (Box 5)
      - "Resistance Tracts 1944", 2 (Box 5)
      - German Air Force. General staff. Berchtesgaden: miscellaneous papers, May 1945 (Box 5)
      - A.A.F.I.S.: printed material, 1942 (Box 5)
      - "Across Enemy Lines: A Three Year Offensive against German Morale by Hansi (Jean Jacques Waltz) & E. Tonnelat, Divisional Interpreters of the Officers Reserve Corps, French Army (Paris 1922)." typescript, mimeograph, 1944 (Box 5)
        Translated into English by Cpl. Roger Starr, MOFE, Washington, 1944
      - Dutch printed ephemera, circa 1941-1944; 7 (Box 5)
      - Netherlands. Underground resistance, medical resistance, 1942 (Box 6)
      - Netherlands. Underground press, undated
      - Press conferences, 1941 (Box 6)
      - Vrij Nederland, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
      - Church resistance, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
      - Het Dagblad, 1945 (Box 6)
      - Het Parool, undated
      - Nederland in Oorlogstijd. Orgaan van het Rijiksinstituut voor Oorlogstijd, undated
      - Reitsch, Hanna: report, 1945 (Box 6)
      - Last days in Hitler's air raid shelter, Hanna Reistch: typescript (2 copies), undated (Box 6)
      - Last days of Berlin: photographs taken George W. Goddard, 1945 (Box 6)
      - Memos, 1943-1944 (Box 6)
      - Military court papers, 1943-1944 (Box 6)
      - USSTAF Intelligence exploitation of the German Air Force-Operation LUSTY, 1945 (Box 6)
      - Italy-partisans and the death of Mussolini and Claretta Petacci: photographs, undated (Box 6)
      - Masterman, John Cecil, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Kaufman, Irving P., 42 Apr 1951 (Box 6)
      - German coin, 1944 (Box 6)
      - German documents, 1944-1945 (Box 7)
      - German documents and photographs, undated (Box 7)
      - Montagu, Ewan: The man who never was, ms, various drafts, circa 1953; 3 (Box 7)
      - Hitler, Adolf: translation of a speech to his generals, 27 Feb (Box 7)
      - Speer, Albert: certificates, undated
      - Dutch resistance manual. "Recipes- domestic science", undated (Box 7)
      - Post World War II. Eisenhower, President and Mrs. Dwight D., 1955-1969 (Box 7)
      - Post World War II. Kroger, Peter J. (Soviet Agent/Lonsdale-Portland Naval Secrets case), 1959, 1969 (Box 7)
      - Moscow News. Purge trials. Proceedings
      - H. A. R. Philby. Draft preface, by K.P., undated (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
      - Checkbook, 1942 (Box 7)
      - Clippings, 1943 (Box 7)
      - Addresses, undated (Box 7)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 7)
      - Patch, undated (Box 7)
      - German security posters, undated
      - Newspapers, undated
      - Wendell L. Willkie Poster, undated
    - Central Intelligence Agency
      - Correspondence, 1947-1993; 2 (Box 8)
      - Notes, undated; 2 (Box 8)
      - Book reviews, undated; 2 (Box 8)
      - Hooke, Nathaniel, undated
      - Peoples' Republic of China Atlas, CIA, Nov 1971
      - White, Stewart Edward: removed from "Our Unseen Guest", 1873-1946
      - Printed ephemera, 1984-1989 (Box 8)
      - Defense Intelligence College, 1985-1990 (Box 8)
      - Defense Intelligence College. Book of Readings. Literature of Intelligence., undated; 5 (Box 8)
      - Houston-Pforzheimer interview transcript, 7 Mar 1983 (Box 8)
      - Masterman, Sir John C. The Double-Cross System: Dusko Popov, the FBI, and Pearl Harbor. 1941, 1983 (Box 8)
      - Contracts, 1984 (Box 8)
      - Press releases, 1954 (Box 8)
      - Intelligence organization and activities corrected proof, undated (Box 8)
      - Colby, William: Honorable Men, typescript, photocopy, 1978; 7 (Box 8)
      - Photographs, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Defense Intelligence College: handbooks and programs, 1980-1989; 4 (Box 8)
      - Exams, 1986-1992; 2 (Box 8)
      - Class Materials, circa 1982-1994; 9 (Box 9)
      - Class Materials, circa 1982-1994; 5 (Box 9)
      - "Fortitude. A history of strategic deception in north western Europe. April, 1943 to May, 1945", undated; 6 (Box 9)
        Typescript, photocopy
      - Pforzheimer, Walter L.: Intelligence at Pearl Harbor: photostat, 22 Aug 1946 (Box 9)
      - U. S. v. Verdugo-Urqyudez: photocopy, 1989 (Box 9)
      - Arthur Alexandrovich Adams, undated (Box 9)
      - Unidentified work: manuscript (partial), undated; 6 (Box 10)
      - Photographs of missile sites in Cuba, 1962 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous printed material, 1981, undated (Box 10)
      - Ultra material: book reviews, undated (Box 10)
      - Book reviews-OSS, by Smith, 1971-1972 (Box 10)
      - Book reviews: miscellaneous, circa 1979-1980 (Box 10)
      - Book reviews-A man called Intrepid, by Stevenson, 1976-1981 (Box 10)
      - Book reviews-Bodyguard of lies, by Cave Brown, 1976 (Box 10)
      - Book reviews-The ultra secret, by Winterbothem, 1976 (Box 10)
      - Bibliography of intelligence literature, 1986-1988; 7 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence and other papers, 1942-1993; 6 (Box 10)
      - First international conference on the history of the European resistance held at Liege and Brussels, Belgium, 14-17 Sep 1958; 2 (Box 10)
      - Second international conference on the history of resistance held at Milan in March, 1961 (Box 10)
      - Lowenthal, Mark M. U. S. Intelligence: Evolution and Anatomy (revised edition): typescript, 1991 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous printed material, correspondence, photographs and notes, circa 1954-1990; 9 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous printed material, correspondence, photographs and notes, circa 1954-1990; 3 (Box 11)
      - Dulles, Alan:The craft of intelligence, advance uncorrected proof, galleys photocopy, 1964; 2 (Box 11)
      - Colvin, John: Twice around the world: typescript, 1980 (Box 11)
      - Masterman, Sir. John C. The double- cross system; original 1945 report (xerox copy), typescript and proofs, 8 (Box 12)
      - Wexley, John: The judgement against Julius and Ethel Rosenberg: correspondence, notes, clippings, legal papers, 1975-1977; 9 (Box 12)
      - Whiting, Charles: Germany: Spy capitol of the world: correspondence, galley, and production files, 1976-1977; 3 (Box 12)
      - Iran: 105 photographs (reproductions), undated (Box 12)
      - Dulles, Alan: The secret surrender, Harpers magazine, 1966 (Box 12)
      - Iraqi money and United States propaganda, undated (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1963-1994; 2 (Box 12)
      - Franklin D. Roosevelt and Tibet, 1959 (Box 13)
      - J. Anthony Pauch, 1949-1953 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, press releases, printed material, 1948-1972; 2 (Box 13)
      - Ronald Reagan-meeting packet, 1980 (Box 13)
      - Hitchcock, 1945-1970 (Box 13)
      - Donovon papers and picture, 1945-1970 (Box 13)
      - Memorandum for the director of Central Intelligence, 1946 (Box 13)
      - Printed material, 1964, 1996 (Box 13)
      - Interview-Ultra Secret, 15 Jan 1986 (Box 14)
      - Lecture Notes, undated; 9 (Box 14)
      - Lecture Notes, undated; 9 (Box 14)
      - Lecture Notes, undated; 8 (Box 14)
      - Care, Wayne: Gentle Insanities (A Novel about Vietnam), undated; 4 (Box 14)
      - Brown, Stuart F. Secrets of Groom Lake, Mar 1994 (Box 14)
      - Gates, Robert M., D. C. I.: Remarks at the (SASA) award ceremony for Dr. Louis W. Tordella, 28 May 1992 (Box 14)
      - Golenievsky, Igor: Draft book review: "Spies without cloaks" by Amy Knight, Spring 1996 (Box 14)
      - Yardley: Herman: The American Black Chamber: proofs, undated; 2 (Box 14)
      - Address to the Los Angeles World Affairs Council, 3 May 1974 (Box 14)
      - Laying of cornerstone ceremony, new CIA headquarters building: photographs, 3 Nov 1959 (Box 14)
      - H-1124 Headquarters Bldg. Sherman Kent: photographs, undated (Box 14)
      - Armed Forces Communications and Electronic Association (AFCEA) Papers, conference, Aug 1985 (Box 14)
      - CIA Miscellaneous clippings, Jan-Jun 1996; 3 (Box 14)
      - CIA Miscellaneous clippings, Sep-Oct 1996 (Box 15)
      - CIA Miscellaneous clippings, May-Jun 1997 (Box 15)
      - CIA printed material, Mar 1996 (Box 15)
      - CIA button, undated; 2 (Box 15)
      - Nathan Hale/CIA coin, undated (Box 15)
      - Cuba patch, undated (Box 15)
      - CIA certificate, 18 Sep 1962 (Box 15)
      - Dublin City University Business School; report, 1996 (Box 15)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1962-1986; 7 (Box 15)
      - Printed Material, including clippings and photocopies, circa 1939-1992; 9 (Box 15)
      - Printed material, including clippings and photocopies, circa 1939-1992; 2 (Box 15)
      - Campaign Poster, Joseph Clark Baldwin, undated
      - Silk screen print by Colonel Randolph Abel, undated
      - Aerial sketch of a harbor city, undated
      - Roger Caseman, lithograph, 1916
      - Intelligence, undated
      - Yale buildings, prints and etchings, undated
      - Newspaper clips and letter, 1847
  - Historical Manuscripts
    - World War I
      - Army Intelligence School, 1918-1919 (Box 16)
      - Photographs: WWI Berlin, Civil War, undated
      - Guide for the Interrogation of German Prisoners-translation from the French, 1 Feb 1918 (Box 16)
      - Mason, Alfred Woodley. World War I intelligence reports, 1916, undated; 2 (Box 16)
      - Mata Hari: photographs, undated; 3 (Box 16)
      - Mata Hari: passport application, 1915-1916 (Box 16)
      - Mata Hari: button, undated (Box 16)
      - Notes, undated (Box 16)
      - Scott, Major General Leno-Mexican border, 1915 (Box 16)
      - Photographs (Box 16)
      - World War I: printed material, 1915-1916 (Box 16)
    - Great Britain, France, and other Subjects
      - Anne, Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, undated
      - British Intelligence. Receipts, undated (Box 16)
      - Bacon, Francis: The Historie of the Regime of King Henry the Seventh (photocopy), undated (Box 16)
      - Cose d'Inghilterra, undated (Box 16)
      - Smith, Matthew and Rev. Richard Kingston-pamphlet exchange (photocopies), undated (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous papers and photocopies, undated; 2 (Box 16)
      - Harrison, William Henry. Indian Wars receipt, 1795 (Box 16)
      - Chesapeake Bay Campaign. Evans, D. L., 1814 (Box 16)
      - Mackey, John: autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Chetwynd, 9 Aug 1704 (Box 16)
      - Grantham, Francis Robinson: autograph letter, signed, to unidentified, 14 Feb 1772 (Box 16)
      - Conrad, Joseph: autograph letter, signed, to Ambroise G. Barner, with printed material, 1923-1988 (Box 16)
      - Boer War spies: photograph, undated (Box 16)
      - Dreyfus photographs, undated; 9 (Box 16)
      - Dreyfus photographs, undated; 3 (Box 16)
      - Dreyfus printed ephemera, 1898, undated (Box 16)
      - Dreyfus letters and related papers, 1900, undated (Box 16)
      - The Provoost Affair-duplicates, undated (Box 16)
      - Rose O'Neal Greenbow, undated (Box 16)
      - Research materials, undated; 7 (Box 16)
      - Kennedy, Dulles, McCone: photographs, undated (Box 16)
      - John André monument: photograph, undated (Box 16)
      - Photographs (reproductions), undated (Box 16)
        McEntee, John; Sharpe, George H.; Walker, Mary E.
      - Spies. Columbia House Video Club press kit, 1992 (Box 16)
      - In Memoriam. Allen W. Dulles: album, 29 Jan 1969 (Box 16)
    - United States, Revolutionary War
      - Addison, A: letters to Joshua Mersereau, 1782 (Box 17)
      - Aitken, James alias John the Painter, undated
      - André, John, 1821, undated; 3 (Box 17)
      - Andréana. Containing the trial, execution, and various matter connected with the history of Major John André: proof, undated
      - Arnold, Isaac N.: autograph letter, signed, to Benson & Lossing re General Arnold's role in first battle of Saratoga, 15 Dec 1879 (Box 17)
      - Secret Service Money in Columbia Centinel, 2 Apr 1803
      - Bissel, Sgt. Daniel. Report of Mission to New York. 1781-1782: photostat, undated
      - Boudinot, Elias. Autograph letter, signed, to Colonel Biddle. Photocopy, 1777 (Box 17)
        Immediate Source of Acquisition
        Accession number 1960 genm 0816-a
      - Bryan, Daniel. Affidavit re Battle of Saratoga, undated
      - Church, R. Benjamin, 1775, 1957-1980; 4 (Box 17)
      - Committee of safety for the state of New York, 1776, 1782 (Box 17)
      - Custis, George W., 29 Jan 1857 (Box 17)
      - Dayton, John: intellgence reports, 1780, undated (Box 17)
      - Grenville, George: report to, circa 1756 (Box 17)
      - Hale, Nathan, 1955, undated (Box 17)
      - Hamilton, Alexander, undated
      - Heath, William, 12 Aug 1778 (Box 17)
      - Henry, John. Case of Documents, undated (Box 17)